SBS strain patterns.
So in this lecture,
we're going to talk
a little bit about
the sphenoid and
the occiput and how
this creates SBS
strain patterns.
I would ask that if you have
the chance to have models
to work with, so I have a
kind of plastic model of the
sphenoid bone and the
occiput that I could kind of
work with, and we'll be kind
of going over the different
strain patterns that could
occur between the sphenoid,
right, and the occiput.
And when we look at it, the
SBS is the junction between
the sphenoid and the occiput
and how this kind of
interplays. And so having that
might be helpful. If you
don't have a plastic model,
it's easy enough to get your
cell phone as the sphenoid
because it's more rectangular
and a circle like a
coaster. Or you could take
a piece of paper and cut out
a really fat letter T and
a round circle and see how
it kind of articulates with
the two bones to best work
and better understand these
patterns. So we're going to
talk a little bit about
osteopathy and cranial field
and key components that Dr.
Sutherland discovered and
described. We're going to
talk about the development
and the different types of
strain patterns at the SPS.
Once we, as we go over these
SPS strain patterns, we're
going to talk about the
motion and movement, but
also how we're going to
diagnose it, especially if we're
holding the head in a vault
hold. So what would we
feel if we're palpating the
head in a vault hold and to
help to diagnose these
strain patterns, we're going
to go over some cases
illustrating some personal cases
that I had applying OMM and
how having an understanding
of these cranial bones
and these strain patterns
and treating it, in addition
to treating other findings,
really helped to address
certain presentations,
especially those associated
with cranial nerve function.
So really having a good
understanding of where the
cranial nerves exit through
the skull, what frame
it passes through, how
a restriction of some of
these cranial bones could
affect that function is
important as we try to
apply OMM and utilize OMM,
especially treating the
head and neck and the
upper back and how that
could affect our patients.
Okay.
So this is one case I had.
I had a two-month-old baby
girl brought in to the
office by her mom complaining
of having a neck being
twisted and a misshaped head.
And so the mom reports
that the baby doesn't
like to turn her head
to the right. and she
heard that OMM could
help her daughter and
she has more questions.
So how do you start?
And so with being able to
communicate, especially
with parents, with patients,
we have to be able to
describe what we're doing
in a competent way, right?
What is OMM? What is
osteopathic cranial medicine,
right? So what is the
approach you use? How could
you explain some of the key
principles and tenets in
lay terms? And then how
could you explain what you're
trying to do to help her
baby with these issues.
So when we start with any
patient visit, whether
or not we're integrating
OMM or not, we want to
make sure we take a
thorough history and conduct
a good physical exam.
More pertinent to OMM and
especially cranial OMM
is whether or not there
is a particular history
of trauma in newborns and
kids and pediatrics where
there are issues with
the pregnancy? Was there
issues during delivery?
Any additional newborn
considerations?
Is the baby having
any trouble feeding,
latching? How is the mom
feeding the baby? Is it strictly
breastfed or is there
additional bottle feeding?
How is the baby in terms of
colic? Is it crying? Is the
baby crying a lot? Is the
baby having wet diapers? Is
the baby defecating okay?
So a lot of history and
questions will help you get
a better understanding of
what's going on and where the
potential issues might be.
Observation, so just
kind of looking, look,
feel, move, right? So
we're going to look, we're
going to see what's
going on. Are there any
asymmetries? Sometimes
when we look at the head,
if there's any asymmetries
of the face, if there's
a flattening of the head,
if there's one side that's
more misshapen, what do
we see from observation?
Palpate and feel
and kind of diagnose
what's going on
and then treatment
is then based on
all these factors.
When you look at a
newborn skull, you
can notice that the
cranial bones are
not necessarily fused
or really articulating.
You don't see those
special articulations
in a newborn because
during delivery, the head
has to mold in order to
pass through the birth
canal. So in a newborn
skull, there's a lot of
open spots and spaces and
a lot of room for this
head to kind of squeeze
through the birth canal.
And so at birth, the
occiput is in four
parts, the sphenoid
in three, the temporal
bone in three also,
the maxilla in two.
There's six fontanels and
there's no mastoid process.
So this is an important
concept to grasp because
when we're working with
newborn heads, there's a
lot of potential areas
where compression and these
forces during delivery,
or even if the baby was C
-section, it is developing
in a tight spot in utero.
And so there could be
compressions and issues and
forces that kind of affect
the head that could be
potentially diagnosed and
treated with cranial OMM.
our mastoid processes right
behind the ear actually
do not develop until the
baby starts to pick up the
head, right? And so we
engage and keeping our head
upwards, and that's going to
create a pull through this
muscle. And as that muscle
gets stronger and develops
more, it starts to pull
on the bone, creating this
actual process on the temporal
bone, the mastoid process.
And so this is a good example
of how the body develops
and how it reacts to
stressors. So bone develops
to the forces that are is
put on it and so one of
the things that we're doing
is to look at what are
these different forces that
are working on the head and
throughout the body and
when treating babies and
kids how can we potentially
address some of these
forces so that there is a
you know there's we take away
any restrictions that
may lead and add to um
asymmetries um and so the quote
is as a bent twig doth the
tree grows, if we are
asymmetric and there's certain
forces in the body that
pulls us a certain way, as
we continue to grow and
develop, we're going to
continue to enhance and grow
more to the right and more
crooked, I guess. So one
of the things that we could
potentially do is to, as
osteopathic physicians,
assess and treat some
of those strains and
restrictions before
the infant grows more
and that strain becomes
harder to take out.
So as I said before, the
sutures there, present,
not overlapping,
because we want the head
to be able to pass
through the birth canal.
In terms of the cranial
bones, our cranial bones kind
of form this helmet. The
skull is the protector of the
brain and the spinal cord.
And so we have our cranial
bones kind of forming this
helmet surrounding our
brain and our central nervous
system. The bones of the
cranial base are formed in
cartilage, right? So this is
kind of important because
when you look at the sphenoid
and the occiput in blue
here, these bones are formed
in cartilage. It's almost
like a continuation of the
spine and so in in some
medical texts historically they
they would call the cervical
vertebra c1 to 7 and
then you have the occiput
which they kind of call c0 and
the sphenoid they call c0
prime right and you can see
how it's pretty much a
continuation of the spinal cord
and then there's a change
in orientation because the
sphenoid then angles forward
and so the sbs vest is
the articulation between the
occiput and the sphenoid.
The vault, which includes our
frontal bone, our
parietal bone,
our squamous portion
of the temporal bone,
the squamous portion
of the occiput here,
kind of forms in
membrane, right? So
here it is in kind of
outlined in red here.
And these bones form in
membrane and all the bones in
general are guided within
the dura that is formed in.
And so when we're treating
the cranial bones, especially
in kids and babies, we're
not trying to move the
bones so much as we are
trying to remove some of the
restrictions that we're
feeling in the cranial dura.
So the primary respiratory
mechanism, which is
described by Dr. Sullivan,
and there's five key parts
of this phenomenon,
right? And so there's a
certain motility of the
brain and spinal cord. So
there's a coiling and
uncoiling of the spinal cord
and brain, which I'll show
you in the next slide.
There's a fluctuation of
CSF associated with this
motility to allow for
circulation of discrepanel
spinal fluid throughout
the brain. There's movement
of the intracranial and
intraspinous membranes.
There's a articular mobility
of the cranial bones. So
these bones that Dr. Sullen
studied, and he saw that
why would, you know, one
of the sutures have gills
similar to gills of a fish,
is that there is the ability
for movement along these
sutures, right? The sagittal
suture being serrated
allows for like a hinge-like
motion. So Dr. Sullen studied
the sutures and studied
cranial osteopathic medicine
and pretty much trying
to disprove that there's
mobility of the cranial
bones and what he found
what there was. And he wrote
down his observations in
what he worked on on himself.
And then finally, there is
a involuntary mobility of
the sacrum between the ilia.
Right. So the sacrum will
move and the sacrum is strongly
connected to this whole
mechanism because it's
connected to the dura that's
coming down from the brain.
And we'll talk about that.
So here is a image you can see.
There were researchers
that looked at MRIs
of the brain. And normally
when you do an MRI
of the brain, you want
to be able to read
your findings. So a
radiologist wants a clear
picture that's not
moving a whole bunch.
Well, these researchers
amplified the movement.
So they were able
to take away the
programming that keeps
the picture more still.
So this amplified image is
the brain moving normally.
It's not that the movement
was amplified. is that they
took away the programming
that made the image more
still to show you how much
motion is actually moving in
our brains, right? And so
there's a lot of motion
going on in the brain, and
this was something that we were
just really looking more
into. And if you read some
of the additional readings
from Foundations, the article
from Hollis King, there's
been a lot of cranial
research going on that's
really interested in how the
brain's moving, what's
happening, especially in NASA
research, looking at astronauts
because they want to know
what happens when there is
no gravity affecting the
brain. Does the CSF still
flow? So really interesting
stuff helping to demonstrate
that the cranial rhythmic
impulse, the PRM is something
that actually exists.
And so I encourage you to
kind of look at this and have
a little bit of confidence
that, hey, I'm feeling
something underneath my hands.
Because when we challenge
you to feel the area of
proximal or the maximal impulse
of your heart, right?
We're going to feel around
the fifth and sixth intercostal
space and feel for where
the heart is beating most
strongly, right? And if
it's more lateral, I might
have a enlarged heart, right?
And so you are feeling
for the heart through your
soft tissue, through your rib
cage, through your intercostal
muscles, through the
lungs, and you could feel
that impulse, right? And so
you have the ability as a
physician to feel things
without actually having to say
you're touching it. Even if
you're touching the spinous
processes and transverse
processes, you have to
sink through all that muscle.
I remember the first day
of lab where you were really
kind of not sure where you
were, what level you were,
and what you're pushing
on. And after having a couple
semesters under your belt
of pushing on different
structures, now you're a lot
more confident in feeling and
diagnosing small asymmetries
of the transverse
process. So with cranial
manipulation, really kind of
give it a chance. This is your
first kind of exposure to
it but it takes a lot of
practice and a lot of hands
-on to really get a sense of
it but that it is possible
and so I wanted you to see
this motion present in the
brain beat to beat they in
the article talk about how
a lot of this motion and
movement they attribute to
circulation and to breathing
but in terms of further
research I think that there's
a lot more research to do
to better clarify what it
is that we're feeling and
working on when we're working
our patients when we're
doing cranial manipulation.
So the hand contacts that
you're going to utilize to
try to diagnose these
strain patterns will be the
vault hold, the frontal
occipital, and the Becker
hold. And so why so many
holds? Well remember the SBS
is in the middle of the
brain. We're looking at how
the sphenoid and the occiput
articulate it's not that
easy to get a sense of
that especially when your
contacts are all on the
vault so if you equate this
to kind of trying to figure
out what's going on in
the ground floor or basement
or foundation of a house
and all you have is the
ability to look at the parts
that you can see right
the above ground part of
the house right and if there's
a crack in the foundation
maybe you'll see it's
kind of leaning a little
bit more to the side. So the
same thing with what we're
trying to diagnose in
terms of the cranial base,
the SBS, where the sphenoid
and the ox put meat, if
there's a twist, if there's
a turn, we might feel that
accommodation in the rest of
the vault or the head. And
so why only have one view,
right, of the head when
you're trying to figure out
what's going on in the basement
floor? So, although most
of our diagnoses are going
to be made with our hands
in the vault hold, it's okay
to get a front and back
look. It's okay to take more
of a look in the back because
that's more important.
It's almost like if you're
going to buy a house and you
don't have the keys to go
in and look at it, what are
you going to do? I'm going
to look in the front window.
I'm going to look in the
side window. I'm going to
look in the back window.
Whatever I can do to get an
idea of how does this house
look from the outside. And if
I palpate it, I want as many
views as I can to try to
get a sense of what's going
on in that ground floor.
So the SPS is the
articulation between a
spinoid and oxput. You
can see here, it's really
in the center of the
head, right? And so it
forms in cartilage,
like we said before. So
it's almost like a
continuation of the spine.
And just like the
spine, there could be
motions in terms of
flexion extension,
side bending and rotation.
So our cranial bones can
move on different axes,
just like the spine can.
And that could result in
different strain patterns.
So here between the
blue sphenoid and the
green occiput is
where we have our SPS.
And we name all the strain
patterns in reference
to how the sphenoid
is moving on the
occiput, similarly to
the rest of the spine. If
I had a T1 FRS right,
that's T1's positional
freedom relative to how
it sits on T2, right?
SPS is right here
in the middle, so
it makes an excellent
reference point.
And our cranium design,
so that when we have
traumatic forces to the head,
it's going to kind of be
driven to the center where
it's absorbed, and it
could kind of shift and
cause issues at the SPS.
Okay.
So, these traumatic forces
could cause different
strain patterns, and Dr.
Sutherland kind of made these
observations on himself
and on his patients. Dr.
Sutherland actually had this
like catcher's mitt that
he kind of put on different
parts of his head and
took a tight belt and
tightened it around his head to
see how that compressive
force would actually affect
him. And in his autobiography
written by his wife,
his wife describes how
she would find him passed
out on the ground after,
you know, putting his own
head in a vice to see what
would happen. And it's
through these observations,
he found that, hey, there's
these different patterns
that could occur based on
what happens between the
sphenoid and the occiput.
And then he also mentions
how most patients will
have a predominant pattern
sometimes from birth or
due to trauma or other
forces during development.
So movement at the cranial
base usually occurs
in a gear-like fashion,
right? So when you
think of gears like a gears
and a watch, the bones
kind of move in opposite
directions so that
it kind of drives
everything forward. And this
drive or motion doesn't
occur only at the SBS.
So here you can see how
the sphenoids kind of
rotating anteriorly, the
occiputs rotating posteriorly.
This is the in the back
of the head. This is
the nose over here. So
as the sphenoid rotates
anteriorly and the occiput
rotates posteriorly,
it kind of has this, this
is moving into flexion.
And then the system goes
into extension where the
sphenoid is going to rotate
posteriorly and then the
occiput is going to rotate
anteriorly, right? So this
gear-like motion occurs
about two transverse axes.
These dots are the axes
of motion and it doesn't
occur in isolation. So as
the sphenoid moves, it also
drives the ethmoid to rotate
in the opposite way. It
then drives the vulmar to
rotate the other way. As
our midline bones move,
it also causes our paired
bones on the side to externally
and internally rotate.
So this whole system is
all moving all at once,
even though we're just
looking at the SBS and
describing what's happening
at the SBS. I want
you to have this more global
look at what's happening
in the big picture
when the SPS is moving.
When the SPS is moving,
so here again moving into
flexion, the sphenoid moves
into flexion, the occiput is
moving into relative extension,
it's going to drive the
base superiorly which then
pulls on the dura which
connects to C2 and 3 and then
down to the sacrum. So as
this pulls on the dura and
causes it to rise, it's
going to cause the sacrum to
rotate posteriorly or counter
-nutate. So this image
shows cranial flexion, the
sacrum is going to counter
-nutate, and then with cranial
extension, the sacrum is
going to nutate or kind of
rotate anteriorly. This
is an important concept to
Grapp's, remembering that if
we have strains here in the
head, it could potentially
affect the upper cervical
region and also all the way
down to the spine. Also, vice
versa, if we have a really
bad sit-down fall or injury
to the buttocks, that could
drive and cause issues
and cause problems with
patients that have headaches.
After delivery, this could
be a big issue because
the sacrum really has
to move and return back
to its normal state postpartum.
And so if the sacrum
tends to get stuck
forward, that could cause
a drag or pulling down
of the whole system here.
And so that's something
that we'll talk about a
little bit more. But it's
just something to consider
that this core link, this
dural link around the
cranium and then attaching
to foramen magnum, then
to C2-3 and all the way down
to the sacrum could have
a lot of different
repercussions if restricted.
All right, so this we just
kind of mentioned before,
these cranial motion patterns
could be due to a lot
of different things, could
be a fascial strain from
below, could be local cranial
semantic dysfunctions,
could be issues in the spine
or pelvis or asymmetry,
right? If I have a short
leg and I'm always tilted
to one side, that's going
to turn my sacrum and that's
going to also cause a
pull going up to the head.
And so sometimes if you're
working on the head and
things are just kind of
really restricted in the
neck, especially the upper
neck, it could be coming
from above or it could
also be coming from
lower. So it gives you
really this holistic global
picture of how any part of
the body could contribute
to different symptoms
that patients are having.
So we explain OMM, the
mom agrees to allow you
to treat. You place your
hands in the vault hold,
and the mom asks you,
what are you feeling for,
right? So what are we
feeling for? So when
we're in this vault
hold, right, our
pinkies are at the
sphenoid, our fingers,
middle finger and forefinger
kind of go in front
of and behind the ear,
which is right here on the
temporal bone. And
posteriorly, our pinky tries
to get to the occiput. So
in the vault hold, we're
getting a sense again of
the vault or membranous
bone. And what we're
trying to get a sense of is
what is moving and what
is not, or if there is a
certain pattern present
to get a sense of what's
going on at the base,
because strains at the base
is what's causing this
accommodation in the vault.
So when we talk about
these strain patterns,
there's some key
things we have to know
about each pattern.
The first one is what
are the axis or axes
if they're multiple?
And what are the
axis of rotation?
So for each strain pattern,
for the sphenoid occiput,
what is the axis for
which that bone is moving
about? What is the direction
of that rotation that
they're moving about,
right? So if they're moving
in opposite direction,
that's good, that's
physiologic. If they're
moving in the same direction,
that's usually bad because
just like gears, they're
going to grind because
they can't go in the same
direction. They have to
go in opposite directions.
We're going to name the
dysfunction or strain
pattern in the direction
of what happens at the
basi occiput relative
to the basi, I'm sorry.
When we name a spinal Like
we said before, we're going
to name what's going to
happen at the segment above
to the segment below. So
the sphenoid is technically
more above the Bayes'
occiput, even though it's more
horizontal. So we're going
to name what happens at
the Bayes' sphenoid relative
to the Bayes' occiput.
We're going to get a sense of
what happens to the cranium.
What will our fingers
feel when there's a
strain pattern present?
What is that vault?
How does the vault feel based
on what's going on at the base?
Describe some of the
source of dysfunction.
And we'll talk about for
each strain pattern, what
could potentially kind of
trigger that or cause that.
And then palpatory diagnosis
to be able to describe
if I was to exaggerate this
motion, what would I feel
if it was a certain strain
pattern in a vault hold.
So we're going to have to
really be able to nail this
down for every single
strain pattern. And I would
suggest as we go through this
PowerPoint, again, working
with the bones, watching the
videos, and also ScholarRx
also has a nice summary
and chart to take a look
through for this chapter,
which we listed in the CPG.
So cranial strain
patterns at the SBS, this
is pretty much all
of them. We have
physiologic, meaning these
are somatic dysfunctions
that are usually
normal if present.
They're kind of like what
happens if my thoracic spine
has a somatic dysfunction
like a T1 FRS right.
They're normal motions of the
spine of how T1 would kind
of move on T2 even though
there might be a motion
preference. So flexion
extension, torsion side bending,
and rotation, these are
physiologic strain patterns.
Non-physiologic strain
patterns, again, like we
said before, they don't
move in a gear-like fashion.
They're usually rotating
in the same direction,
causing this kind of barrier,
and usually it's maladaptive.
It's usually secondary
to some sort of trauma,
and there's significant
restriction of motion secondary
to these strain patterns.
So vertical shears, lateral
shears, and compression
are non-physiologic strain
patterns. I'm going to go
into more detail there.
So flexion extension is
what we're kind of feeling
for when we first put
our hands on. It's, you
know, a nice way to start
because this is something
going on all the time,
similar to breathing.
So when we take a deep breath
in and exhale, our spine
does this also. There's a
little bit of a straightening
and then a little bit of
a curvature whenever we
inhale and exhale. And this
pattern of respiration is
also occurring in the head.
So there's this respiration
that occurs when we
breathe through abdominal
breathing, but our head and
our cranium is also undergoing
this PRM, flexion extension,
at a rate of 6 to 12.
And that's something
that we could try to get
a sense of and palpate,
right? And so as the
the cranium goes through
flex and extension,
our sphenoid and occiput will
move in opposite directions
along two parallel transverse
axes. So you have to
get oriented to the image
here. When you see this
image, the sphenoid is on top
of the occiput, and this is
what you're looking at in
pretty much a vault hold.
If someone was laying on a
table in front of me, I will
see the sphenoid more
superior towards the ceiling,
the occiput towards the table,
and there's two transverse
axes, but we name the axes
for anatomical neutral,
right? So if the person's
standing up, it's two transverse
axes. Just because they're
laying down, it doesn't
make it horizontal axes, if
that makes sense. So we're
naming it relative to
anatomical neutral. These are
two transverse axes. The
sphenoid and occiput are moving
in opposite directions, right?
So this is a physiologic
strain pattern. And so
what happens to the head
when this occurs is that
there is a change in shape.
Like I said, when you work
the sphenoid and occiput, it's
not just the sphenoid and
occiput moving. The vault
and all the other bones
around the face, the head, are
accommodating to that main
motion in the base, okay?
So there might be a preference
to flexion or extension.
Just like in the spine, we
have a segment that could
be considered more flexed
or extended. And if there
is a preference that it is
considered a dysfunction.
So flexion at the
SPS, these are the two
transverse axes,
these dark dots here.
The sphenoid is rotating
anteriorly, right?
Again, orient yourself.
The nose is over here,
inion, and the back of
the head is over here.
So as the sphenoid
rotates anteriorly and the
occiput rotates posteriorly,
rotating in opposite
directions, the SPS
is then going to rise.
And then the pair bones
will externally rotate.
So if you pictured
like a temporal bone on
this side, a temporal
bone on the other side,
as we go in towards
flexion, it's going to
externally rotate. And
so I'm going to try to
grab my model here, right?
So here is my model.
I'll do the best I can
here. This is the sphenoid.
This is the occiput, right?
And so as I go into flexion,
that's flexion, right? So
the sphenoid will rotate
anteriorly, the occiput
rotate posteriorly, and then
extension is the opposite
way, right? So like I said
before, if you have some
sort of model to play with,
whether it's a phone and
a coaster, I have two
transverse axes. And if you
have pipe cleaner or pen, you
could kind of see those
axes of motion and movement
again, okay? So this is
what that image on the slide
is showing. So what happens
when I go into flexion,
right? I'm going to have
a decreased AP diameter
and vertical diameter,
and I have an increased
transverse side diameter
because the temporal
bone is kind of externally
rotated. So you're going
to get a head that kind
of looks like Ernie,
okay? So Ernie has a flexion
head or flexion dysfunction,
okay? And so a wider
diameter, transverse diameter,
and decreased vertical
diameter and AP diameter.
So this is flexion dysfunction.
Extension dysfunction,
the same two transverse
axes, but now the sphenoid
is going to rotate posteriorly
and so will the occiput,
right? So So now that
we're having the sphenoid
rotating posteriorly and the
occiput rotating posteriorly,
again, greatly exaggerating,
it's going to drop
down the SPS relatively.
You can see how it kind of
moves inferiorly. Okay. So
as I drop it down, that's
going to make everything
more narrow and taller,
right? So there's decreased
transverse diameter because
the paired cranial bones
will internally rotate. So
you're going to get more
narrow and then you're going
to have increased AP and
vertical, right, of the
head. So this is going to
be a Burt head if you're a
Sesame Street fan, if you
didn't know who that was.
So what will this look
like if we were palpating
someone's head in the
vault hole, right?
So we talked about the
axes, we talked about
the motion moving in
opposite directions.
Now we're going to talk
about what happens when we're
palpating someone's head
and we feel the head go
into flexion or extension.
And so in flexion, we're
going to feel our fingers
kind of spread out, right?
So if you picture your
fingers on the, here's your
pointer finger and on the
occiput is your pinky.
when the sphenoid rotates
anteriorly and the
occiput rotates posteriorly,
it's going to make
your finger spread out.
It's going to increase
the distance between your
pinky finger and your
pointer finger, right?
So our fingers are going
to spread out and kind
of move a little bit
inferiorly,
okay? So it's going to
kind of spread out and move
inferiorly a little bit, whereas
when we go into extension,
again, our pinky finger
is now sphenoid, I'm
sorry, pointer fingers on
sphenoid pinky fingers on
occiput all our fingers are
now going to come closer
together it becomes more
narrow so our fingers are going
to come closer together and
come up towards the head
and if you play with this
on your model right if i
picture where my fingers
would be as i do this or you
can have a partner kind of
take the cranial bones and
kind of put it in the
position of a vault hold and
put your pinky on the greater
wing and your i'm sorry
i keep saying that your
pointer on the greater wing
and your pinky on the occiput
you can see how when i
move into flexion our fingers
are going to spread out.
When I move into extension, our
fingers are going
to come together.
So really playing with the
models will give you a better
sense of what's going on
than just looking at these
images and pictures. So
again, flexion, our fingers
are going to spread out and
move down towards the feet.
And extension, our fingers
are going to come together
and come up towards
the head. But our palms
are not going to
approximate. Our palms
are not going to twist.
It's just a finger
spread and down,
finger spread and up.
Okay, so that's how
our fingers will
kind of feel when
we're sensing a strain
pattern for flexion
and extension.
So you're palpating the
heads and your fingers on
your right hand feel like
they spread out more and feel
like they're being pulled
down and inferiorly towards
your feet. So this is
pretty much a typical exam
question trying to get a
sense of do you understand
if you're palpating some
sort of a stream asymmetry or
strain how could you equate
that to a strain pattern
that you're feeling right
so this is going to be
something that you're going
to have to be able to do
based on the descriptor of
what you're feeling in the
vault hold so this pattern
is a side bending and
rotation strain pattern right
and there could be a pull
from below especially for
this case here in this baby,
we knew that the baby had a
tighter sternocleidormastoid
muscle, and so that
could kind of pull the
head towards one side, causing
things to feel a little
bit more pulling down
towards the feet on one side.
So here was the baby that
we're treating, and again
you can see a little bit
more of a misshaped head
you can see that the baby
definitely preferred um
a preference to left rotation
and we tried to actually
bring the head straight
the baby was not happy
so in a side bending
rotation pattern this is
one of the physiologic
strain patterns so everything
occurring at the
sbas at the sbs is
technically physiologic so
we have two vertical axes
these blue dots here are
two vertical axes, and
our sphenoid and occiput
are going to rotate
in opposite directions
along these two vertical
axes. And when we
do that, you can see
how that would kind of
cause a side bending,
right? So if I'm rotating
the sphenoid one way and
the occiput the other
way, it's going to cause a
side bending of the cranial
bones. And so you're
going to get a side bending,
and then what happens
is with the side bending,
a rotation occurs of both
bones in the same direction
across the AP axis. So
this is probably the most
confusing strain pattern
because there's two
different motions going on,
right? So you're going to
have side bending occurring
along two parallel vertical
axes, and then you're
going to have rotation
occur about an AP axis.
The side that it is more
convex on is the side
that you're going to name
it for. And that same
convexity side is the
side that will rotate down
towards the feet. So we're
going to see that here.
So the rotation here, you
can see it's rotating on
two vertical axes, causing
it to be wider here on the
left side. So here's the
two vertical axes. I'm
rotating the sphenoid and
the occiput in opposite
directions, and that's going
to cause this, I'm sorry,
this circle here is actually
for the axis of rotation
for AP. So this is the
rotation, and then this one
is going to rotate this
way. The occiput's rotating
this way. You can see how
that would cause this side
to gap and open up. And so
even though the sphenoid
looks like it's side
bending right. We don't call
it that because we call it
for the side that's more
convex, the more wider
side. And then both of these
segments are going to
rotate on one AP axis to the
right. So if the feet is
here, it's going to rotate
down to the feet on the,
I'm sorry, on the left side.
Say that again.
Two vertical axes.
We're going to rotate in
opposite directions to
cause a side bending.
This segment looks like it's
side bending, the sphenoid
looks like it's side
bending to the right, but we
are going to name it for
the side of the convexity,
and this is the left side,
because the sphenoidy occiput
will rotate on this AP
axis rotating to the left.
So the side bending rotation
is named for the side
of the convexity, similar
to how we name scoliosis
in the spine, the
direction of the rotation,
okay?
Don't get confused and
call this a right side
bending because it's, I
kind of think about cranial
side bending rotation as
coupled, okay? And we're
going to name it for the
side of the wider side
or the side that's more
down towards the feet.
So here's the image.
We rotate about two
vertical axes. So here
you can see the sphenoid
is rotating towards
the right and here
the occiput is kind
of rotating this way.
I got to make sense of
these arrows. But the
sphenoid output will rotate
on two vertical axes.
So if I take my model
here and give you a good
view of it, good. So
here's the sphenoid, here's
the output. If we take
two vertical axes, like
in and out of the screen,
and kind of bend it in
opposite directions, it
causes a side bending.
OK, so if I kind of rotate
the segments in opposite
directions, you can see how
it causes a side bending
to one side and then the
side that's fuller. So here
we're going to roll down
to the feet. So that's
what's causing the side
bending rotation. So here,
sphenoid occiput rotating in
opposite directions, so this
is going to rotate, sphenoid
is going to rotate this
way, and the occiput is
going to rotate this way.
The image here is
showing the AP rotation.
That's why I'm
confused. I'm sorry.
So these white arrows
is showing the turn of
the sphenoid occiput,
showing its rotation.
Okay? But you can see how
it causes a side bending
convex left. So this is a
left side bending, and this
is a right side bending
rotation strain pattern.
The next image will show
you that axis, AP axis,
that causes the rotation.
That's where these white
arrows come in play.
Sorry for the confusion.
So the right side bending
rotation is convex right,
and the left side bending
rotation is convex left.
Okay,
so these strain patterns
will feel, so if we go back
to here, if my finger on
the left hand, my pointer
finger is going to be on
the greater wing, and my
pinky is going to be on
the occiput, if my hand was
here, the left side would
feel like it's spread out
more. See how the distance
between the greater wing
and the occiput is increased
due to the side bending,
and on the other hand,
the greater wing and the
occiput are going to be
closer together. So one side
is going to feel more spread
out, the left side. The
right side is going to
feel more closer together.
And since now the rotation
is going to cause the
left hand to feel like it
rotates down to the feet,
my left hand is going to
spread out, go down to the
feet. My right hand is going
to come closer and come
up towards the head. So
that is a left side bending
rotation and then vice
versa. In a right side
bending rotation, my fingers
on the right hand will
spread out and kind of go
towards the feet. and my
fingers on the left hand
will come close together
and come up towards the
head. So that's what you're
seeing in this image. Right
side bending rotation,
left side bending rotation.
And so you really are
going to feel the fingers
spread out on the side
of convexity and then go
down towards the feet.
That down and out feeling.
Okay.
Visually sometimes if
you see an asymmetry that
could be due to these cranial
strain patterns. Like I
said before, what's going
on at the SPS will affect
all the cranial bones,
including the face. And
our orbit has seven bones
that help to create it. And
these strain patterns
can potentially drive and
make an orbit seem a little
bit higher, more wider.
Our zygomatic rim or our
cheekbone might seem a
little bit higher or more
flattened. Our chin might
seem deviated more to the
right or left. our ear,
because of how the
temporal bone is externally
rotated or internally
rotated, it might seem like
it's sticking out a little
bit more or kind of closer
to the head. So you're
not going to get a test
question specifically on
how you identify a side
bending rotation, but just
keep in mind that if you
see asymmetries in the
face that that may point
to some sort of craniosomatic
dysfunction present.
okay so as you saw in
the images the baby has
decreased rotation to the
right what muscle could
be involved right so we've
kind of said before the
sternocleidoid muscle
could potentially be
involved here what cranial
nerve is associated with
right and so the
sternocleidomastoid is innervated
by cranial nerve 11
right and where does it
exit and how what other
nerves kind of exit with
it. And we'll have some
images with that. So, um,
our cranial nerve 11, the
spinal accessory innervates,
um, the sternocleidomastoid
muscle. And so when
this muscle is spasmed or
tightened, it's going to
cause a side bending
towards and a rotation away.
And so, um,
babies sometimes, uh,
could be to a lot of
different reasons may
potentially have a restricted
sternocleidomastoid
muscle, right? It's just
naming all the attachments
of this muscle.
And it exits through the
jugular foramen, which before,
remember the image in
newborns, the occiput is in
four parts, the temporal bones
in three, and this really
kind of precarious region
where the occipital condyles
and the petrous portion
of the temporal bone meet
forms the jugular foramen.
And through this exits cranial
nerves 9, 10, and 11. 11
being the one important for
sternocleidomastoid. It also
has where 90% of our venous
blood drains through this
foramen. So restrictions
in this area could really be
something to pay attention
to, this area being the
occipital mastoid suture,
right? The occipital, this is
occipital bone, and this is
the mastoid bone on the
temporal bone, occipital
mastoid suture, OM suture. And
we'll have different techniques
to kind of really look
at that and address that,
right? So if we
have issues with
cranial nerves 9, 10, and 12,
these are key cranial
nerves that could be
affected and could cause
issues with infants with
latching and with feeding
and swallowing, right?
So nine and 10 exit from
the jugular foramen,
right? And so here, this
was the occiput on the
baby, and this is the
occiput on the adult, and
this is that occipital
mastoid suture, right?
Between the mastoid
portion of the temporal
bone coming down, and
jugular foramen is there,
and it's over here.
So again, very key
area, And if we
have restrictions
here, compression along
the area, that
could cause issues.
The hypoglossal canal exits
from foramen magnum. And
so, again, since these
occipital condyles are in parts,
sometimes these condyles can
get jammed in babies, and
that could cause irritation
of these nerves, causing
issues with, again, latching,
swallowing, and feeding.
The jugular foramen also
is where cranial nerve 10
exits. It's cranial nerve
10 is really important
because it supplies parasympathetic
innervation to almost
every organ in our chest
and gut, right? It provides
parasympathetic innervation
to the heart, to the
lungs, to our colon,
to our GI system. And
parasympathetic innervation,
remember, is rest and digest.
When we're sick, when we're
ill, when we're trying
to fight or flight, we're
kicking in our sympathetic
nervous system. this is
all part of our autonomic
nervous system, which we
can't control. Our body is
pretty much autonomic. It
happens automatically. So
if we have issues with
parasympathetic innervation,
or if we have restrictions
of that occipital
mastoid suture affecting
the exiting of cranial
nerve 11, I'm sorry,
cranial nerve 10 and
its passageway down the
neck, there might be
musculoskeletal
restrictions that's
preventing the optimal
function of that nerve.
So it is something that
we've done research
studies on that have
shown improvement of
parasympathetic heart rate
variability, a decrease
in arrhythmias with
treatment of this region.
So we had the baby in for
several visits. And one
of the things that we
were able to do is kind of
track how much asymmetry
was present in the head
and based on imagings and
photos we could see that
initially when we first
started treating the baby
there was definitely a
severe asymmetry and after
several visits one
two three by the third
visit the baby
definitely had decreased
spasms of the sternocleidomastoid
helping to resolve
that toricollis and the
head was more in a natural
position. You remember
in the picture before,
when we tried to turn the
baby's head to the right,
the baby was crying. And
by the third visit, the
baby didn't have a problem
really turning the head
side to side. And the
asymmetries really decreased.
Kind of makes sense
because when you're laying
on one side with your
tight neck muscle, that's
going to cause compression
of that side and that
could cause more of a
flattening on that area.
So taking that image
and continuing with the
case, we treated the
patient's torticollis. The
mom still complained
that, hey, the baby still
kind of has a little
bit of a misshaped head.
And we'd mentioned before,
if we look at a baby's
face or a person's face,
that these asymmetries
might point to something.
So here we're looking at
the baby's face and you
can see it seems like one
side seems a little higher
than the other, right?
If you look at the eyes
and you could look at
the face, right? So what
might be happening here.
So these visual findings
kind of points towards
a torsional strain
dysfunctions. We're going
to talk about what a
torsion dysfunction is.
A torsion dysfunction
is still a physiologic
dysfunction because the
sphenoid and occiput rotate in
opposite directions. The
axis is a anterior posterior
axis from nasion, right?
The nasion is where the
nasal bones and the frontal
bone meat and epiceon,
right? And so that is the
posterior aspect of the
foramen magnum. So this imaginary
line is how the sphenoid
and occiput are rotating
on in opposite directions,
thus a physiologic
strain pattern, right? So
here from a superior
view, you can see this is
the sphenoid and it's
rotating in one direction
and the occiput is
rotating in the other.
And so we name it for the
side of the higher greater
wing. You can see how this
would be higher, relatively
higher or more towards the
apex of the head compared
to the occiput. Again, we
name it for the freedom.
Here, as it rotates,
the right greater wing
would be higher. So we
call this a right torsion.
So there's a
preference to right
rotation of the
sphenoid on the occiput.
And so again,
AP axis and rotation of the two
bones in opposite directions.
What do we feel? So here,
this one's a little trickier.
We're going to have our
hands. One hand is going to
kind of have all its
fingers kind of feel like
it's rolling up towards
the ceiling. And the other
hand is going to have all
its fingers rolling down
towards the floor. We want
to almost like imagine
like we have a pen between
our hands or a reflex
hammer. And we don't want to
tilt in any way. So keeping
our hands kind of parallel,
we're just going to
roll one hand up towards
the ceiling and the other
hand down towards the floor.
And that's what you're
going to feel. Since
our fingers are on the
greater wing, if I roll my
right hand higher, that's a
right lateral strain. I'm
sorry, a right torsion.
Again, torsions, talking
about lateral strains.
So torsions,
physiologic strain patterns,
we're going to roll
our right hand up, that's a
right torsion. And we roll
our left hand up, that's
a left torsion. And the
opposite hand kind of goes
the opposite way. Okay,
greatly exaggerating what
you're feeling in the
head, but that's the general
pattern that you'll feel
in the vault when you
have this strain pattern.
Okay, and so like we
mentioned before, when
there's a misshaped head,
that condition is called
plagiocephaly. There's
an asymmetry of the head.
There's also
flattening of the head,
brachiancephaly, right?
And so these are things
that we could potentially
treat with OMM.
Back in 1992,
the American Academy
of Pediatrics
recommended infants be
placed back to sleep.
So that positioning on
the back puts a lot of
pressure on the back of
the head. And we said
before how the cranial
bones are still kind of
moldable, especially at
birth. And so babies being
put back to sleep helped
to decrease the rate of
sudden infant death
syndrome or SIDS. And so
it's a good thing. but
at the same time, it also
increased the incidence
of plagiocephaly because
it's important to give
the baby tummy time when
awake so that they're
not constantly laying on
the head and flattening
key areas. And like we
said before, if there's
an asymmetry like a
torticollis, that's going
to cause a flattening
of the head a little bit
more on one side than
the other, causing this
kind of misshaped head.
So treatment options
include OMM. Here's my son
Benjamin treating Lydia
when she was little.
Or you can put a helmet
on the head, which will
kind of help mold ahead
but also kind of restrict
growth and so the other
thing is it's really
hard to be compliant with
the helmet because you
have to keep it on like
23 hours throughout the
day and so there was a
more recent article showing
that the helmets don't
necessarily show much
improvement compared to
just not having a helmet and
we're doing some really
interesting studies with OMM
looking at how kind of like
what I showed you with our
study which was a case study
But now there's prospective
studies where parents are
putting a more validated
device, not device,
really. It's kind of like a
hairnet, and that hairnet could
kind of read the asymmetries
of the head very easily
and very safely. And it's
really amazing what we could
really do with technology
these days to get a better
sense of measuring some
of the outcomes that we're
looking for with treatment.
one thing you really have
to be careful of is if
you do see plagio to make
sure that it's not cranial
stenostosis which is
early closure of a suture
and that could also cause
a misshaped head so if
you do have that suspicion
if you're treating
there's no real improvement
then that's something that
might need a referral to
pediatric neurosurgery
okay so that was
a long case but it
helped to illustrate
a bunch of the
physiologic strain patterns.
I'm going to talk about
a really interesting case
that I had. It was a six-year
-old girl, problem with her
visions, decreased abduction
of her right eye when we
are asked her to look to
the right, okay? So remember
that extraocular muscles
are also innervated by cranial
nerves, and so this was
a really interesting case.
The patient actually had
issues with her extraocular
muscle, thus causing that,
specifically the lateral
rectus or superior
oblique muscle. I wasn't
sure exactly which one.
Might have been lateral
rectus, I think, because
that's what pulls the
eye more laterally.
And so what type of strain
pattern could affect these
cranial nerves, right? So
pretty much all of them
can, but one of the main
things to think about is how
these cranial nerves, 3,
4, and 6, which innervate
the extraocular muscles, all
pass through the superior
orbital fissure of the
sphenoid, right? And so
taking a better look at the
sphenoid bone, right? This
is the sphenoid bone. Here
it is from a superior view.
Here it is from a posterior
view. And so this bone,
if you look from the
posterior view, that's the
superior orbital fissure.
And that's where the cranial
nerves are exiting from the
brain and going into the
orbit region to innervate
the extraocular muscles.
So our patient actually
was diagnosed with
Duane's Retraction
Syndrome. Very, very unique
case. I've only seen
it once in my career.
The mom brought the
baby in and she wasn't
actually a baby, she was
six years old, but was
diagnosed really early
on. And so what's
interesting about this
case is that a lot of times
there is an issue with
the abducens nerve,
which is responsible for
abduction of the eye,
right? And they actually
talk about it when you look
at the syndrome that there's
dural attachments would
cause the nerve to angulate
as it passes underneath the
petrosphenoid ligament
or Gruber's ligament. The
petrosphenoid ligament is
ligament between the temporal bone
and the sphenoid bone. And
because of how that nerve
passes, sometimes it can be
compressed, thus causing an
issue with innervation of
the lateral rectus muscle.
Here's a better look at
it, right? So the different
cranial nerves has its origins
in the brainstem, right?
These nuclei, and they
kind of combine and form
these nerves. And you can
see the ocular motor up here,
trochlear nerve up here.
But look at cranial nerve
6. It kind of takes this
really roundabout route
getting to the superior
orbital fissure. It dips down
first, then comes up, and
then passes through here.
And so, sorry, hit the
button there. So cranial
nerve 6, as it passes
through, here's another
image. That's cranial
nerve six, it passes under
this petrosphenoid ligament,
right? So here's the
sphenoid, right? This is
the right side to kind
of clarify things. And
here's cranial nerve three
and here's cranial nerve
six, right? And as we said
before, six kind of comes
from below, comes up
and then catches up with
things, but sometimes it
tucks underneath this
petrosphenoid ligament. Here's
the petrous portion of
the temporal bone and
that's that Gruber's ligament
and you can see how it
kind of compresses that.
So now imagine the sphenoid
additionally having some
sort of strain there.
And that strain could then
lead to additional tension
and issues as this nerve
tries to pass through.
And so these were our
findings on our case. And our
patient had this right
lateral strain pattern, which
is non-physiologic. So
what's a right lateral strain
pattern. It is one of these
non-physiologic strain
patterns, vertical shears,
lateral shears, and compression
are the non-physiologic
strain patterns. And so non
-physiologic strain patterns
occur when these bones
move about in the same
direction, which again, gears
can't move in the same
direction, or it causes a real
shearing force. That's
why they're called shears,
vertical shear, lateral shear.
This is pathologic. This is
something that's not good,
that doesn't normally
occur in the body, usually
due to some sort of external
force, okay? So vertical
and lateral strains are non
-physiologic. They're usually
due to some sort of trauma,
typically symptomatic and
interfered with normal
motion and thus having a
pathologic effect. So lateral
strains. Our patient had
a lateral strain pattern.
When I put my hand on the
head, I felt like totally like
a parallelogram occurring
okay and so a parallelogram
is our hands kind of moving
in the same direction
the lateral strain
pattern when we talk about
motion of the bone occurs
about two vertical axes
where did we see this before
we saw this in the side
bending and rotation
so in the side bending
rotation the two bones
rotated in opposite directions
and that caused a side
bending right And that's
pretty normal. So if we
go back to our model here,
if you take your own model
and try to rotate in,
get a good grasp on this.
If you take your own
model and try to rotate in
opposite directions, it
causes a side bending.
But try to rotate in
the same direction. So
if I rotate the sphenoid
one way and the opposite
the same way, you see
how it causes a shearing
force across, right?
And so that shearing
force occurs when the
bones rotate the same way.
We name this strain
for what happens at the
basi sphenoid, how the
basi sphenoid moves,
right? And so there's been
some kind of discussion and
debate sometimes through
different teaching manuals
and journals. um when
especially with non-physiologic
strains because they're
they're so complex and there's
so many different traumas
and we think about you know
these different traumas and
blows a lot of times it's
not going to be perfectly
lateral there might be some
twist to it there might be
some of a more of a 3d um
impact right nothing's ever
perfectly straight across
from our temporal bone And so
sometimes our results might
necessarily fit the
expected parallelogram, but
understand that there might
be some shifts in the greater
wing where you might feel
like a parallelogram, but
the basal sphenoid may not
be moving the same direction
really as the greater wing.
And so you might have some
findings that aren't
exactly textbook. And that's
really the extent that I'm
going to go into that, that
sometimes if you're putting
your hands on it doesn't
really fit textbook, there
might be something else going
on, especially for history
of trauma. And know that
there might be other
variations that other textbooks
explain, especially of lateral
strains. But to be clear,
especially for examination
purposes and for board exam
purposes, we're going to
name the lateral strain for
the direction that the basies
sphenoid moves towards.
So in these images of
lateral strains, you
can see how the
sphenoid is rotating one
way and the occiput
is rotating the same
way, non-physiologic,
two vertical axes.
That's going to cause
this shearing force
to occur where you
see here A and B.
Okay? And so when you have
this shearing force occur,
the lateral strain here
is a left lateral strain
because the Bayes'
sphenoid, I'm sorry, right
here where the kind of
pointer is, that's the
Bayes' sphenoid you can
see is relatively more
to the left compared
to the Bayes' occiput,
okay? So this is a
left lateral strain,
and then the same thing
happens on the other side.
If we're rotating the
other way, about two
vertical axes, it's
going to cause the
right basysphenoid
to be relatively more
to the right compared
to the basy occiput,
right? So this is a
right lateral strain,
but the greater
wing is to the left.
Okay. And this greater
wing is our fingers,
pointer fingers
on the sphenoid.
So how is this going to feel.
So when we have a lateral
strain, we have this
parallelogram head. So our
fingers are going to feel like
they both kind of tilt to
one side. So if you had
that pen again, right,
you're just going to not do a
torsion up and down, but
side to side, right? Tilting
side one way, tilting to
the side the other way.
And we do see this sometimes
with plagiocephaly.
Again, like we said
before, that kind
of flattened head
because we're laying more
on one side. So if I
have a lateral strain,
my pinky fingers going to
the right and my pointer
fingers going to the left,
I really have to kind of
not confuse myself because
I know that it's a confusing
topic. So index finger
is going to move to the
side of the greater wing.
The pinkies are going to
move to the opposite side.
So the movement of the
pinkies is usually the
direction of the basysphenoid,
right? And so we're going
to name it really for our
pinkies, right? So if I'm
tilting my hand, and so in this
instance, right, I'm tilting
my fingers to the right.
My pinkies are going to the
left. This is a left lateral
screen, but my greater
wing is going to the right.
And that's the top view,
even though it's a mirror
image, so don't get confused.
If, if I point to the left
with my pinkies and my,
I'm sorry, if I point to
the left of my pointer fingers
and my pinkies are going
to the right, then that
is a right lateral strain.
Name it for the
direction for which your
pinkies are moving
towards in general, okay?
So those are lateral strains.
we treated the patient and
afterwards the patient had
improvement and more symmetry
with eye gaze laterally
which was kind of cool
it was a pretty cool case
we put a poster together
for that just another thing
with the eye personal story
um i was playing racquetball
i got hit in eye with the
racket i had increased
intraocular pressure
intraocular pressure and so for
um one week i was putting
eye drops in hoping to
get the pressure down wasn't
really going down and um
it happened that during
lunchtime dr etlinger came
in and i asked him to
treat me and um so with his
experience he treated me
with cranial osteopathic
medicine around my orbit
around my eye. Um, there's
a actual advanced face course
that he helps to teach.
Um, so he treated all
these, um, dysfunctions that
he found around my eye.
I've been going to the
ophthalmologist for a week
that day after work, when
I went to ophthalmologist,
my pressure was normal.
And from that day on, my
pressure continued to be
normal. And so there's a
lot of different things that
cranial osteopathic medical
medicine could treat. Um,
you can make a whole
specialty out of it. And so I
was truly amazed by the
power of it on myself. And
sometimes I still amaze
myself when I treat patients
and I use OMM in general
and incorporate cranial
osteopathic medicine and their
headache goes away and they
feel great after just one
treatment. I'm not saying
that's a guarantee on all
patients, but if you have
the understanding of
what's going on and develop
your skills in applying
OMM to the whole body,
incorporating some of the
understanding of what you're doing
with the cranial aspect
also, you could really help
a lot of your patients in
a lot of different ways.
Okay.
Last case. So we have
a 50-year-old man comes
in with dizziness and
persistent ringing in his
ear after he tripped
and hit his chin on the
dining room table as he
fell to the ground. Okay.
What cranial nerve could
be potentially involved?
So again, based on the stem,
what are the key symptoms,
knowing the symptoms,
what kind of ties into
ringing the ear or tinnitus,
or what ties into dizziness,
right? And so most likely
cranial nerve eight.
What foramen does it
exit? What cranial bone is
that, right? So it
exits from the internal
acoustic meatus, and that's
the temporal bone. And
what strain pattern
could have happened here,
right? So based on the
story, we talked about the
vector of the force
getting hit on the chin,
midline blow, he might have
created a non-physiological
strain pattern in a
vertical setting, right?
So cranial nerve 7 and
8 exit from the internal
acoustic meatus. So cranial
nerve 7, ****** nerve,
when that's impaired, a
lot of times you might
see Bell palsy, right? And
so that's ****** drooping,
right? Loss of muscle
strength in the face.
cranial nerve eight is
responsible for sound and
equilibrium, right? So in
this case, that ringing in
the ear, that kind of
dizziness could be attributed
to that. So this is the
temporal bone. It's a very
important bone. It houses
the semilunar canals,
which kind of give input for
balance. And so restrictions
of this temporal bone
could really impact a
lot of different things,
including cranial nerve 7
and cranial nerve 8 as it
passes through this bone.
Here that is,
here it is, right?
You can see cranial nerve 7 and
8 as it passes through there.
Just so you can see here,
we talked about 3, 4, and
6. Also, V1 passes through
the superior orbital
fissure. You have V2 going
through foramen rotundum, V3
going foramen ovale. So
your trigeminal nerve exits
through these foramen in
your sphenoid. So patients
with trigeminal neuralgia,
the sphenoid bone is also
something to really take a
look at. Your optic canal
is up here, cranial nerve
two, and crivoform plate,
your ethmoid, is cranial
nerve one. And we've been
working a lot with that.
We had one case where we
had a patient post-COVID
that lost sense of smell and
treatment of the cranial
system, really focusing on
the front of the face, and
the ethmoid bone helped
restore the sense of smell
sooner than later, the
average, for those with loss
of smell with post-COVID.
so going back temporal bone
we're looking at cranial
nerves seven and eight
and this impact midline
impact sometimes could cause
a shearing of the cranial
bones along the two
transverse axes so whether we
see this before we saw this
in just routine flexion
extension however now the
bones are traveling in
the same direction and
when you travel in the same
direction like we said
before, non-physiologic, not
good. We name it for positioning
of the basi sphenoid.
And so this could be
resulted to a blow to the
head from below or from
above, like you stand up too
quick and you hit the
cabinet, right? That could
drive the sphenoid bone
inferiorly and throw things
off from moving in your
usual flexion and extension.
So here is a superior
vertical strain. So my
sphenoid is rotating anteriorly
and so is my occiput.
So you can see how the
basi sphenoid is higher
than the basi occiput here.
So that's why this is a
superior vertical strain.
In an inferior vertical
strain, the sphenoid is
rotating posteriorly and the
occiput is rotating
posteriorly. So you can see
how now the sphenoid, its
basi sphenoid is going to
be more inferior to the
occiput. But if you look at
where your fingers would
be, like here if my finger's
on the greater wing of
the sphenoid, my pinky's
on the occiput, as it
rotates anteriorly in a
superior vertical strain,
all my fingers are going to
feel like they're rotating
down towards the floor.
And here if my finger's
on the greater wing and my
pinky's on the occiput,
as I move into an inferior
vertical strain, both
of these bones rotating
posteriorly, all my fingers
are going to feel like they
are rotating up towards
the ceiling right so when
you're feeling the strain
pattern of volt hold even
though the sphenoid is
more inferior right this is
a sphenoid this is the
occiput this i know this is
sphenoid because that's
what the cellotercica where
pituitary sits so the
sphenoid here is more
inferior relative to the
occiput right because
it's rotating um posteriorly
our fingers are going
to go all feel like
it's going up towards
ceiling so when an inferior
vertical strain all
our fingers will feel
like they're rotating um
inferior vertical strain
all our fingers are going
to feel like they're going
up towards the ceiling in
a superior vertical strain
all our fingers going to
feel like they're going down
towards the table there's
an error here in the text
both fingers will rotate
posteriorly as the fingers
are rotating up towards
the ceiling so that is to
be corrected up towards the
ceiling I will correct that
on the PowerPoint, okay?
So make sure that in frivolous
strain, all the fingers
are going up towards
the ceiling. This is a
mistype here, and I'll correct
that in the PowerPoint.
So this is my son.
And so you can
see from anterior
and side view,
it seems like the
head is very slopey
forward. So if I put
my hand in a vault
hold, maybe all my
fingers will feel what?
They'll feel like it's
sloping downward. So if
all my fingers are feeling
like they're sloping
downward, what kind of
strain pattern could it be?
So all these fingers sloping
downward could be a superior
virgo strain. You see how
the sphenoid is rotating
anteriorly, the occiput
is rotating anteriorly. So
my finger on the greater
wing, my finger on the occiput
is all going to feel like
you're going down towards
the floor. Kind of like what
the head looks like here.
Okay.
Happy to report his head
looks much more normal.
We did spend a lot of
time getting him treated.
Okay.
So you palpate the
patient's head and you don't
feel any motion. Other
than doubting yourself and
thinking you're a horrible
osteopath, what else
could be the reason why
you don't feel anything?
So the final strain pattern
here that's non-physiologic
is the SBS compression.
This usually occurs
with really a trauma where
I fall on the back of my
head or the head goes
through the car windshield
because you're not belted.
Some sort of front back.
It could be really any
direction, but really jammed
together, causing a lack
of motion or movement.
Really, when I put my
hand in a vault hold or
Becker or any hold, really,
it just feels really
dense with very little
excursion. You really could
barely feel the PRM due
to this compression.
So an SBS compression,
usually some sort of
major trauma. I've seen
this in patients that
have chronic pain due to
some severe head injury,
and it does take a lot
to try to treat this
and try to improve the
motion in this region.
Okay, so those are all the
different strain patterns.
It's important to understand
these strain patterns
to help address some of
the restrictions that might
occur at the base in
treating the cranial base.
We affect all the different
bones where these different
cranial nerves that
exit. We affect the brain
itself, right? We've done
a lot of different studies.
We use NYT also on
Parkinson's, on concussion, and
how OMM could help treat
post-concussion syndrome.
We have a glymphatic system
that drains in the superior
sagittal sinus, right? And
so that superior sagittal
sinus is within the dura
surrounding the brain. And
we have techniques that we
said before that could help
treat the cranial bones,
which lie within that dura.
And really what we're treating
are these dural strains.
Using utilizing this treatment
to kind of help balance
autonomic system, enhance
circulation and blood flow
and glymphatic drainage,
and also improve venous
sinus drainage, which is the
blood flow surrounding the
head, and also ****** sinus
drainage, right? So we
have our ****** sinuses, our
frontal sinus, our maxillary
sinus, our maxillary
sinuses drain is higher than
where the cavity is. And
so if there's a restriction
of motion or movement,
that might prevent proper
sinus drainage and lead to
sinusitis and sinus pains.
And so a lot of different
things that we could address
by better understanding
what's going on in the head.
There are some
absolute and relative
contradictions. you have to
be really careful treating
patients with acute
intracranial bleeding,
any sort of skull
fracture, any sort of acute
cerebrovascular accident.
That said, I work at
the hospital with Dr.
Ellinger at St. Barnabas
Hospital, and we've
treated patients with
acute intracranial
bleeding that's controlled.
I've treated patients post
-stroke, and part of it is
also really knowing what
you're doing and your comfort
level. I wouldn't say be a
beginner and go ahead and
go at it, but the
textbooks do state absolute
constrications, acute intracranial
bleeding, skull fracture,
acute cerebrovascular
accident. That said, we
are trying to talk to
the authors of the next
foundations to say that
perhaps it should be relative
because we need to do
a little bit more of
a chart review to show
that what we do is safe.
Relative
contraindications include
coagulopathies.
You're worried about
anybody who may potentially
develop a bleed,
any space-occupying
lesions like tumors of the
brain, and any sort of
increased intracranial
pressure.
Really, really understand
and know the cranial nerves,
review it, know their
names, know their function,
know what happens if we
did restrict that cranial
nerve, and then know how
it's exiting and its path,
because then you'll know what
bone to kind of really focus
on when treating patients
with cranial dysfunctions.
And so kind of take a
look at this, look at your
your nanny books, get a
sense of it, look at the
PowerPoint again, and look
at that picture. How do these
cranial nerves exit? What
bone is it associated with?
And how can we address
certain restrictions that
might remove any sort of
musculoskeletal restrictions
that are, that's impacting
the flow of those nerves?
This was taken from
the Osteopathic
Cranial Academy website.
There are just so many
things that treatment of the
cranium could be tied into
because you are, you are
affecting the cranial nerves,
cranial nerves, you're
affecting the central
nervous system, you're
affecting the spinal cord.
So you're affecting the jaw,
right? There's a lot of
dental applications, TMJ.
Through the vagus
nerve, you could
affect digestion,
feeding in kids.
Neurologically,
there's many, many
applications, including
concussion and
headaches, which we've
done studies on here.
A lot of things we could
do with the pediatric
population, geriatric
population too, and then
respiratory, pretty much
any system, any patient
population, any age, any
system where you have something
where there's some sort
of autonomic dysfunction
or anything going on
with the cranial bones
that have an involvement
with the cranial nerves.
So in summary,
osteopathy and
cranial field, which
was called before
in the past, or
osteopathic cranial
manipulative medicine,
which is preferred now
used in the Journal of
Osteopathic Medicine,
could be utilized for
many different conditions,
as you just saw.
Understanding the motions
and patterns that occur
at the SPS could help you
with diagnosing these cranial
dysfunctions and help
you start your treatment.
Understanding the anatomy
of the cranial nerves and
path will help guide your
treatment, and applying
these techniques can help
support your patient's
health and help them heal
from different injuries.
Okay, here's the
lecture feedback form,
and I thank you
for your attention.
Best of luck in lab.